<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philippines | Ernest Guevarra</title>
    <link>https://ernest.guevarra.io/tags/philippines/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ernest.guevarra.io/tags/philippines/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Philippines</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Ernest Guevarra 2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 20:37:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ernest.guevarra.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Philippines</title>
      <link>https://ernest.guevarra.io/tags/philippines/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bagyo</title>
      <link>https://ernest.guevarra.io/post/bagyo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 20:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ernest.guevarra.io/post/bagyo/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;One would be hard-pressed to think of any other event or phenomenon more universally experienced by Filipinos than a cyclone or what we call &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;bagyo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (pronounced /baɡˈjo/, [bɐɡˈjo]). My earliest memory related to cyclones was when I was 4 years old and my older brother and I were put into an empty plastic drum to float above flood waters pushed along by our mother. My mother recounts how happy and excited my brother and I was being inside that drum, oblivious to the strong gusts of wind and heavy rains outside. She did her best to steady the drum and shield us from the wind and rain while she waded through chest-deep flood waters to get to a place of refuge. As I grew up, cyclones would provide interesting chapters into my formative years. I still recall the joy of having school cancelled when the incoming cyclone was determined to be too strong and potentially unsafe followed by an immediate realisation that I would just end up being stuck at home and unable to play because of the harsh conditions outside and the constant possibility of flooding. In my second year of medical school, I volunteered to live in a small remote fishing village in the main northern island of the Philippines. The village lies along the usual path of cyclones that develop on the Philippine Sea to the east. As to be expected, midway into my time there was when I experienced the raw power of cyclones. Over a three-day period, two typhoon category cyclones made landfall near the area of the fishing village and with the eye of the storm, the spot with the lowest pressure and fastest sustained wind speed, passing very close by. This was very transformative and made the experiences of those in the margins - whether physical, social, or economical - tangible and real for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, having lived almost half of my lifetime outside of the Philippines, I have gone places where I’ve experienced other life-changing and values-defining events and phenomenon. These, along with my cyclones experience, continue to shape and inform my notion and understanding of fairness, diversity, and equity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is from this background that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://panukatan.io/bagyo&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; R package&lt;/a&gt; was borne out of. Just like a songwriter’s lyrics and melody for a dearly beloved or a poet’s ode to their muse, this package is a nod to my youth and a loving embrace to my motherland. I’ve always thought of how good it would be to have a dataset that I, and others like me, will be able to relate to. And today the &lt;a href=&#34;https://panukatan.io/bagyo&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; R package&lt;/a&gt; has just been released on &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;CRAN&lt;/a&gt;. I hope this dataset can be an adjunct to the well-established &lt;a href=&#34;https://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-devel/library/datasets/html/iris.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;iris&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; dataset and to the currently popular &lt;a href=&#34;https://allisonhorst.github.io/palmerpenguins/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;palmerpenguins&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;about-the-bagyo-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About the &lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; package contains the &lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; dataset. This dataset was taken from annual reports on Philippine tropical cyclones prepared and released by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pagasa.dost.gov.ph/&#34;&gt;PAGASA&lt;/a&gt; at its &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pagasa.dost.gov.ph/tropical-cyclone/publications/annual-report&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; in PDF format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the reports are in PDF format and the information described above are in tables within the documents, scripts for scraping the desired data were developed and implemented to arrive at the &lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; dataset. The data scraping script can be viewed &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/panukatan/bagyo/blob/main/data-raw/process_data.R&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following information is available from the dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;year&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;category_code&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Tropical cyclone category code&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;category_name&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Tropical cyclone category name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Name given to the tropical cyclone by Philippine authorities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;rsmc_name&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Name given to the tropical cyclone by the Regional Specialized Meteorological Centre (RSMC)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Date and time at which cyclone enters Philippine area of responsibility (PAR)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Date and time at which cyclone leaves Philippine area of responsibility (PAR)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;pressure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Maximum central pressure in &lt;em&gt;hPa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;speed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;left&#34;&gt;Maximum sustained wind speed in &lt;em&gt;km/h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This metadata can be viewed in R through a call to &lt;code&gt;?bagyo&lt;/code&gt; in the R console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst tropical cyclones have affected the Philippines far earlier than 2017 and more currently than 2020, official and publicly available data for the information described above is only available in the reports for years 2017 to 2020. Earlier documents of this annual reporting pre-2017 have been produced but are not available on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pagasa.dost.gov.ph/&#34;&gt;PAGASA&lt;/a&gt; website. These reports of the tropical cyclone season (re-started in 2019) are published within two years after the termination of the season. Hence, the most recent report is only up to 2020 for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is expected that reports for 2021 onwards will continue to be published and made available by PAGASA. As such, the &lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; package and the &lt;code&gt;bagyo&lt;/code&gt; dataset within it will be updated accordingly. Continued efforts are also being taken to find sources of information for years preceding 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>covidphdata: An Interface to the Philippines Department of Health COVID-19 Data Drop</title>
      <link>https://ernest.guevarra.io/post/interface-doh-covid19-data-drop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ernest.guevarra.io/post/interface-doh-covid19-data-drop/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.doh.gov.ph&#34;&gt;Philippines Department of Health&lt;/a&gt; has made COVID-19 related data publicly available as part of its mandate to promoting transparency and accountability in governance. The Philippines COVID-19 Data Drop is distributed via &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt; with latest updated data provided daily (generally). Data from previous days are archived and also made available through &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt;. This package provides a coherent, robust and performant API to the latest and archived Philippines COVID-19 data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;motivation-and-development-history&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation and development history&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early April 2020 as part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://como-ph.github.io&#34;&gt;CoMo Philippines&lt;/a&gt;’s contribution to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tropicalmedicine.ox.ac.uk/news/como-consortium-the-covid-19-pandemic-modelling-in-context&#34;&gt;CoMo Consortium&lt;/a&gt;’s work in COVID-19 modelling for the Philippines context, we developed an &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; package called &lt;a href=&#34;https://como-ph.github.io/comoparams&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;comoparams&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that provided &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; functions for access, handling and processing of relevant data required for COVID-19 modelling parameters for the Philippines. Within the &lt;a href=&#34;https://como-ph.github.io/comoparams&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;comoparams&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package was a set of functions developed to interface with the then &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/OfficialDOHgov/posts/announcement-covid-19-data-drop-now-accessible-onlinecovid-19-related-data-now-a/3227811310563432/&#34;&gt;newly-announced Philippines Department of Health Data Drop for COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;. From then until late June 2020, we continued maintenance of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://como-ph.github.io/comoparams&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;comoparams&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package. Specifically, the set of functions for interfacing with the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; required several functions updates (see history of issues and changes to the package &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/como-ph/comoparams/issues?q=is%3Aissue&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) in relation to noted issues with the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; system and the data it provides. A good discussion of some of these issues by the &lt;strong&gt;UP COVID-19 Pandemic Response Team&lt;/strong&gt; can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.up.edu.ph/prevailing-data-issues-in-the-time-of-covid-19-and-the-need-for-open-data/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Other issues that required syntax-breaking changes to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://como-ph.github.io/comoparams&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;comoparams&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package functions were related to how the DoH Data Drop was released and distributed. Earlier during its first release, the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; was distributed through &lt;em&gt;Google Sheets&lt;/em&gt; via a single non-changing link. This was for both latest release and the archived data. A few weeks later, the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; was moved to &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt; again via a single non-changing link for both the latest and the archive data. A month or so after, release of the latest &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; was distributed through a single link that changed during every release (usually daily). The archive data, on the other hand, was distributed through a different but constant &lt;a href=&#34;https://bit.ly/DataDropArchives&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; distribution system has since remained as such up to date though the archive data now only includes the current month archive compared to what it was in late June 2020 when all previous months of archive data were available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, given the still persistent issues raised with regard to the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; system and the datasets it distributes, we felt it was important to create a separate focused &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; package just for accessing, handling and processing of the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; that can be universally used by other &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; users regardless of their ultimate end-use for the data (e.g., reporting, visualisation, modelling, etc.). We also wanted to contribute to the work of fellow scientists and researchers in the Philippines whom we are familiar with and whom we know use &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; for the epidemiologic analysis work they perform which they share with the general public in the Philippines. From our own experiences of dealing with the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt;, we felt that it would be extremely helpful for fellow scientists and researchers who use &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; to have consistent and performant data access, handling and processing functions to interface with the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; that can potentially reduce the daily and/or weekly workload of producing COVID-19 analysis and reports and streamline their routine analytical workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this end, we took inspiration from the functions we developed in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://como-ph.github.io/comoparams&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;comoparams&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package and developed this &lt;code&gt;covidphdata&lt;/code&gt; package based on the following &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; package design principles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;use of a &lt;strong&gt;modular and refactorable approach&lt;/strong&gt; to determining and developing the functions required;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;creation of an &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;-based &lt;strong&gt;robust and performant application programme interface or API&lt;/strong&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt;-based &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;application of &lt;strong&gt;modern data handling and processing techniques&lt;/strong&gt; available in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;; and,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;output of &lt;strong&gt;coherent and compliant data structures&lt;/strong&gt; ready for various applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we want to contribute to both the &lt;em&gt;public discourse&lt;/em&gt; and to the &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;strong&gt;open data&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;open science&lt;/strong&gt; in the Philippines and encourage others to do the same. Our group’s codebase for our work on COVID-19 modelling (primarily in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; language for statistical computing) is available publicly via &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/como-ph&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; including the one for the &lt;code&gt;covidphdata&lt;/code&gt; package (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/como-ph/covidphdata&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/como-ph/covidphdata&lt;/a&gt;). Our hope is that by creating this package and making its use available to all &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; users and its codebase open source, we can standardise accessing, handling and processing of the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; thereby providing transparency to the approaches applied to the data before it is analysed or visualised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-does-covidphdatado&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does &lt;code&gt;covidphdata&lt;/code&gt;do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;covidphdata&lt;/code&gt; primarily provides functions that serve as low-level wrappers to specific &lt;a href=&#34;http://googledrive.tidyverse.org&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;googledrive&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; package functions that support the access to files and folders contained in a &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt; given that the &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; is distributed through this platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the &lt;code&gt;covidphdata&lt;/code&gt; package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides functions (&lt;code&gt;datadrop_id*&lt;/code&gt;) to dynamically retrieve unique &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; file and folder identifiers used by &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides a function (&lt;code&gt;datadrop_ls&lt;/code&gt;) to list the files and folders within a specified &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; folder in &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides a function (&lt;code&gt;datadrop_download&lt;/code&gt;) to download a specified file within &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt;; and,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Provides functions (&lt;code&gt;datadrop_get&lt;/code&gt;) to retrieve a specified file within &lt;strong&gt;DoH Data Drop&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Google Drive&lt;/em&gt; into &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about the &lt;code&gt;covidphdata&lt;/code&gt; package - how to install in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;, how to use the package, and how to contribute to its development and testing - visit the package website at &lt;a href=&#34;https://como-ph.github.io/covidphdata&#34;&gt;https://como-ph.github.io/covidphdata&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do not go gentle into that good night</title>
      <link>https://ernest.guevarra.io/post/do-not-go-gentle-into-that-good-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ernest.guevarra.io/post/do-not-go-gentle-into-that-good-night/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I didn’t realise how much I would be affected by the current and continuing struggle of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-54519788&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reina Mae&lt;/strong&gt; as a political detainee arrested based on suspicious charges of unlawful possession of firearms and explosives and as a grieving mother of three-month old &lt;strong&gt;Baby River&lt;/strong&gt; whom she gave birth to while in custody, separated from her after a month and who just recently died of pneumonia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve experienced a rush of memories from 20 years back when I was still a medical student in my clerkship and internship years. Whenever I was not on duty on a Saturday or a Sunday, I joined a health and human rights organisation in their routine outreach work to political detainees still languishing in prison. I usually worked alongside the organisation’s senior doctor or nurse in looking after the general health and well-being of the political detainees as they awaited their cases and appeals for release to be heard by the courts or for a decision for their release to be made. But more than the health checks that I helped in providing for them, it was the visit itself from our group that made all the difference for the political detainees - a reaffirmation that their colleagues and brothers and sisters in the struggle have not forgotten and continue to represent and advocate for them to be appropriately recognised as political detainees rather than common criminals and thus be afforded their rights as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a young person and just about to finish medical school, the little that I have been able to contribute to help them in their struggle was returned to me through a wealth of learning of the political work that they did and its importance in the bigger struggle for a more just and fair society and country. They afforded me with their camaraderie and kinship sharing their sadness for not being with their family and not seeing their children grow, their grief for loved ones who’ve passed whom they have not had the chance to be with prior, but also their continued optimism for their eventual release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 20 years of finding my own causes and hopefully contributing my own share to the bigger struggle for a just and fair society as a public health practitioner, I am struck to my core after reading about the callousness and the indignity of what Reina Mae and Baby River have been made to endure. This has brought out an anger inside me that I thought I’ve been able to let go. An anger that is shared by so many others within the Philippines including fellow health professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelson Mandela has once said that, &lt;em&gt;“There can be no keener revelation of a society’s soul than the way in which it treats its children.”&lt;/em&gt; Let us not let the few in our society who chose to ignore the needs and rights of Baby River and separated her from her mother, Reina Mae who has equally been denied her rights, define who we are as a society. &lt;strong&gt;Rage, rage against the dying of the light&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
