<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ernestguevarra | Ernest Guevarra</title>
    <link>/authors/ernestguevarra/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/ernestguevarra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ernestguevarra</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Ernest Guevarra 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 00:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>ernestguevarra</title>
      <link>/authors/ernestguevarra/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do not go gentle into that good night</title>
      <link>/post/do-not-go-gentle-into-that-good-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/do-not-go-gentle-into-that-good-night/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I didn’t realise how much I would be affected by the current and continuing struggle of &lt;strong&gt;Reina Mae&lt;/strong&gt; as a political detainee arrested based on suspicious charges of unlawful possession of firearms and explosives and as a grieving mother of three-month old &lt;strong&gt;Baby River&lt;/strong&gt; whom she gave birth to while in custody, separated from her after a month and who just recently died of pneumonia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve experienced a rush of memories from 20 years back when I was still a medical student in my clerkship and internship years. Whenever I was not on duty on a Saturday or a Sunday, I joined a health and human rights organisation in their routine outreach work to political detainees still languishing in prison. I usually worked alongside the organisation’s senior doctor or nurse in looking after the general health and well-being of the political detainees as they awaited their cases and appeals for release to be heard by the courts or for a decision for their release to be made. But more than the health checks that I helped in providing for them, it was the visit itself from our group that made all the difference for the political detainees - a reaffirmation that their colleagues and brothers and sisters in the struggle have not forgotten and continue to represent and advocate for them to be appropriately recognised as political detainees rather than common criminals and thus be afforded their rights as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a young person and just about to finish medical school, the little that I have been able to contribute to help them in their struggle was returned to me through a wealth of learning of the political work that they did and its importance in the bigger struggle for a more just and fair society and country. They afforded me with their camaraderie and kinship sharing their sadness for not being with their family and not seeing their children grow, their grief for loved ones who’ve passed whom they have not had the chance to be with prior, but also their continued optimism for their eventual release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward 20 years of finding my own causes and hopefully contributing my own share to the bigger struggle for a just and fair society as a public health practitioner, I am struck to my core after reading about the callousness and the indignity of what Reina Mae and Baby River have been made to endure. This has brought out an anger inside me that I thought I’ve been able to let go. An anger that is shared by so many others within the Philippines including fellow health professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelson Mandela has once said that, &lt;em&gt;“There can be no keener revelation of a society’s soul than the way in which it treats its children.”&lt;/em&gt; Let us not let the few in our society who chose to ignore the needs and rights of Baby River and separated her from her mother, Reina Mae who has equally been denied her rights, to define who we are as a society. &lt;strong&gt;Rage, rage against the dying of the light&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We are Katilingban</title>
      <link>/post/we-are-katilingban/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/we-are-katilingban/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;katilingban&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;[ka-ti-ling-ban]&lt;/em&gt;: (n.) A Cebuano word meaning 1) a group or a community of people; 2) society, organisation or club.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at times of extreme social struggle and difficulty that we are reminded of the &lt;em&gt;primacy of the collective&lt;/em&gt; and the value of working towards the &lt;em&gt;common good&lt;/em&gt;. The current global health crisis brought about by the &lt;strong&gt;COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt; pandemic along with the social upheaval caused by the continuing and persistent racial injustice in the United States recently sparked by the death of George Floyd at the hands of a white police officer and which has grown into a worldwide &lt;strong&gt;Black Lives Matter&lt;/strong&gt; movement are the signs of the times. And these are the times when the power of collective action towards the common good is even more crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is against this backdrop that I, together with three other colleagues, have founded &lt;strong&gt;Katilingban&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;a collective of multi-disciplinary experts and practitioners in public health and nutrition&lt;/em&gt;. Though coming from different nationalities and diverse backgrounds and experiences, one of our main commonalities is our community-based orientation - from a doctor who ran a community-based mental health programme for civil war-affected children and youth in the Philippines, to a public health practitioner who studies and works with communities to understand their context to inform health and nutrition programming, to a community health and nutrition expert who has performed multiple coverage assessments and evaluations of community-based nutrition programmes in the past decade illustrating how the community aspect of these programmes has mostly been poorly done, and to a nutrition data expert who has implemented numerous nutrition surveys to aid in the design and planning of nutrition programmes advocating for more community participation in programme design and planning. And it is this community-based orientation that inspired us to form our own collective, to form &lt;strong&gt;Katilingban&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the remainder of 2020, we would like to once again emphasise the importance of coverage of health and nutrition programming more so in the light of the COVID-19 pandemic. The pandemic has disrupted health and nutrition in more ways than just the infection itself. The global focus on COVID-19 has potentially further widened disparities in other health and nutrition outcomes particularly in low and middle income countries through a variety of mechanisms. We would like to collaborate with other organisations and researchers who are keen on assessing the impact of the pandemic on various aspects of health and nutrition in low and middle income countries. And given the limitations posed by the pandemic, we would like to explore the use of relatively new or less utilised modalities of primary data collection and to test and utilise other analytical techniques on already existing secondary data and routine programme data taht would allow us to still examine and understand the on-going health and nutrition situation other than COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in collaborating? &lt;a href=&#34;https://katilingban.io/#contact&#34;&gt;Contact&lt;/a&gt; us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
